<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>VVestward for smelts. Or, the vvater-mans fare of mad-merry vvestern wenches whose tongues albeit like bell-clappers, they neuer leaue ringing, yet their tales are svveet, and will much content you. VVriten by Kinde Kit of Kingstone.</title>
            <author>Kinde Kit, of Kingstone.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14984</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25292</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101857</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837660</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837660</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1998</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14984)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1998)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1016:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>VVestward for smelts. Or, the vvater-mans fare of mad-merry vvestern wenches whose tongues albeit like bell-clappers, they neuer leaue ringing, yet their tales are svveet, and will much content you. VVriten by Kinde Kit of Kingstone.</title>
                  <author>Kinde Kit, of Kingstone.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Purslowe] for Iohn Trundle, and are to be sold at his shop in Barbican, at the signe of the No-body,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures:  A-E⁴ F² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Short stories, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1998:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1998:1"/>
            <p>Weſtward for Smelts.</p>
            <p>OR, The VVater-mans Fare of mad-merry VVeſtern wenches, whoſe tongues albeit like Bell-clappers, they neuer leaue Ringing, yet their Tales are ſweet, and will much content you.</p>
            <p>VVritten by Kinde <hi>Kit</hi> of <hi>Kingſtone.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>smelting scene</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn Trundle,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Barbican, at the Signe of the No-body.</hi> 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1998:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1998:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EADER, for thy pleaſure haue I (this once) left my Oare and Stretcher, and ſtretched my wit, to ſet downe the honeſt mirth of my merry Fare Fiſhwiues: if I haue pleaſed thee, I am fully contented, and aske no more for my Fare: if not, I haue loſt both my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and the reward I hoped for from thee, and doe vow neuer more to trouble you with any other words than, <hi>Will you haue a paire of Oares?</hi> But my hopes are better, cauſe you (looking at my hands) for no other then Freſh-water Poetry, ſhall not be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: and therefore not offended. So without any fawning tricks (which are things vſed too much in theſe times) I take my leaue, wiſhing thee health; and if thou ſit hard, my Boats Cuſhions. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours to command,</hi> Kinde Kit of Kingſtone.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1998:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1998:3"/>
            <head>VVESTWARD FOR SMELTS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N that ſelected time of the yéere, when no man is ſuffered to be a Mutton-monger, without a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all priuiledge from thoſe in authoritie: and no man is licenſed to inioy a fleſh-bit, but thoſe who are ſo weake, that the very ſight contents their appetite: yet euery man deſireth fleſh that is no whore-maſter. When Butchers goe to Beare-baytings on Thurſdayes, leauing their Wiues and Prentiſes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king pricks, in ſhops halfe ſhut vp, like houſes infected of the plague: when at the ſame time Fiſhmongers are in their height of pride, daſhing water in their ill-ſented ſtreet, like a troope of Porpoſes at Fluſhing head. When the Cookes ſpits are hung vp like Pikes in a Court of gard, and their dripping pans (like Targets in a country Iuſtices Hall) bee mouldie for want of vſe. At this time of the yeere the Pudding-houſe at Brookes-wharfe is watched by the Hollanders Eeles-ſhips, leſt the inhabitants, contrarie to the Law, ſhould ſpill the bloud of innocents, which would be greatly to the hinderance of theſe Butter-boxes. In briefe, it is the Kitchin-ſtuffe wiues vacation, which makes them runne to the hedge for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter maintenaunce. Euery one knowes this was Lent-time, a time profitable (onely) for thoſe that deale with liquid commodities: for none but Fiſh muſt be eaten, which neuer doth digeſt well (as ſome Phyſicions of this time hold opinion) except it ſwimme twice after it comes forth the water: that is, firſt in Butter, ſo to be eaten: then in Wine or Beere after it is eaten: Now how chargeable this laſt liquor is, aſke in priſons of prodigals who haue paid well for it: and how profitable to the ſellers, aſke of thoſe Aldermen that haue had their beginning by it.</p>
            <p>In this time of Lent, I being in the Water-mans Garriſon of
<pb facs="tcp:1998:4"/>
Quéene-hiue (whereof I am a Souldier) and hauing no imploiment, I went with an intent to incounter with that moſt valiant and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Champion of Quéene-hiue,<note place="margin">The Red Knight is an Ale-houſe Signe at Queene-hiue, where the Water-men vſe to tipple.</note> commonly called by the name of the <hi>Red Knight;</hi> one who hath ouerthrowne many, yet neuer was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe diſmounted, or had the leaſt foyle: yet doth hee deny to grapple with none, but continually ſtandeth ready to oppoſe himſelfe againſt any that dare be his oppoſite, againſt whom he hath alway the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: for if they yeeld to him in the right of his conqueſt, hee taketh from them a certaine ſumme of money, according to the time that they haue held out: but if they ſcorne to yeeld, hee not onely taketh from them their goods, but likewiſe with his ſore blowes he taketh from them their ſences, making them often to fall at his Caſtle gate for dead: voiding at the mouth abundance of filth cauſed by his ſtrokes.</p>
            <p>I had not long held combate with this Knight, but my man came running in, telling mee he had a Fare Weſt-ward. This newes made me giue ouer the combate, but with ſome ſmall loſſe, for hee would not loſe his ancient priuiledge; ſo I giuing him two pence, had frée liberty to paſſe his gates, where I found my Fare, which were a company of Weſterne Fiſhwiues, who hauing made a good market, with their heads full of Wine, and their purſes ful of coine, were deſirous to goe homeward. We agreed quickly, and the Boy layd the Cuſhions: I put them in the Boat, and we lanched into the deepe, <hi>Neptune</hi> bee our ſpeed, <hi>Weſtward for Smelts.</hi> Hauing paſſed the troubleſome places of the Thames (where the Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries runne to and fro like Weauers ſhuttles) and being at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> I might perceiue all my Fiſhwiues begin to nod. I fearing they were in a ſound, with my Oare ſprinkled a little coole water in their faces, which made them all to awake: which I perceiuing, bid them rowze themſelues vp, and to continue their mirth, and kéepe them from melancholy ſleepe, and I would ſtraine the beſt voice I had. They prayed me ſo to doe: but yet not to clay their eares with an old Fidlers Song, as Riding to <hi>Rumford,</hi> or, All in a Garden Greene I ſaid, I ſcorned ſo to do, for I would giue them a new one, which neither Punke, Fidler, or Ballad-ſinger had euer polluted with their vnſauourie breath: the ſubiect was, I told them, of a Seruingman &amp; his Miſtris. They liked the ſubiect well, and intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me to proceed, promiſing that each of them would requite my
<pb facs="tcp:1998:4"/>
Song with a Tale. I ſaid, I was content, and would thinke well of their requitals. So they being all ſtill, I began in this manner:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>FAirer then the faireſt,</l>
                     <l>Brighter then the rareſt,</l>
                     <l>Was the comely creature which I ſaw.</l>
                     <l>Her lookes they were attractiue,</l>
                     <l>And her body actiue,</l>
                     <l>All beholders ſences for to draw.</l>
                     <l>I honour ſtill this comely creature,</l>
                     <l>And euer will doe while I liue:</l>
                     <l>And for her grace and goodly feature,</l>
                     <l>All honours due to her I'le giue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When I firſt beheld her</l>
                     <l>O had <hi>Cupid</hi> will'd her,</l>
                     <l>For to fauour him that lou'd her beſt!</l>
                     <l>Ioyes had me poſſeſſed,</l>
                     <l>Sorrowes had not preſſed,</l>
                     <l>On my grieued heart that takes no reſt.</l>
                     <l>I thinke on her with adoration,</l>
                     <l>I muſing ſet vpon her beauty,</l>
                     <l>On her is all my meditation,</l>
                     <l>Yet more to her were but my duty.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>She her ſelfe is witty,</l>
                     <l>All her parts are pretty,</l>
                     <l>Nature in her forme hath ſhewed her skill:</l>
                     <l>Her bright beauty maz'd me,</l>
                     <l>All her parts well pleaſ'd me:</l>
                     <l>For of pleaſant ſights I had my fill.</l>
                     <l>Then 'gan her hand for to vncouer</l>
                     <l>Her whiteſt neck, and roundeſt pap:</l>
                     <l>Then gan I farder to diſcouer</l>
                     <l>Moſt pleaſing ſights, yet wayl'd my hap.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Still I ſtood obſcured,</l>
                     <l>And theſe ſights indured:</l>
                     <l>Yet I to this goddeſſe durſt not ſpeake.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:1998:5"/>Had I made a tryall,</l>
                     <l>Her moſt ſad deniall,</l>
                     <l>My obſeruant heart oh it would breake.</l>
                     <l>Therefore will I reſt contented,</l>
                     <l>With priuate pleaſures that I viewed,</l>
                     <l>And neuer with loue will be tormented,</l>
                     <l>Yet loue I her, for that ſhe ſhewed.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Hauing thus ended, I aſked them how they liked my Song? They ſaid little to it. At laſt, Well, quoth a venerable Matron (or rather a Matron of Venery) that ſate on a Cuſhion at the vpper end of the Boat, let vs now performe our promiſes to him in telling euery one her Tale: &amp; ſince I ſhall land firſt, I will begin firſt: ſo the Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhall be ſure of his requitall promiſed by vs, which ſhall bee Fiſhwiues Tales, that are wholeſome, though but homely: ſo ſot merrily to <hi>Brainford,</hi> my maſters.</p>
            <p>I liked this well, and cauſe I would heare them all out, I made but ſlow haſte: And 'cauſe you ſhall haue ſome knowledge what rare piece this Fiſhwife of <hi>Brainford</hi> was, I will deſcribe her beſt and outward parts.</p>
            <div type="tale">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This Fiſhwife ſtout,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That led the rout,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>At <hi>Brainford</hi> dwelt.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She ſometime dealt,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>With fleſh exchange:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But now (though ſtrange)</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She gaue it ore,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And knew no Whore.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She was well ſet,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her body met,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Two yards was found:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her head from ground</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Was not ſo hie.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She went awry.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her face was great.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She ſtunke of ſweat.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Let it ſuffice,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She had large eyes:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And a low brow,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Much like a Sow</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That ſindg'd had bin.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Appear'd her chin:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For it was hayr'd.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her noſe was mar'd</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For't had a gap,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>By great mis-hap:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>As you ſhall heare,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Then giue good eare.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <pb facs="tcp:1998:5"/>
               <head>The Fiſhwifes Tale of <hi>Brainford.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN <hi>Windſor,</hi> not long agoe, dwelt a Sumpter man, who had to wife a very faire (but ſomething wanton) creature; ouer whom (not without cauſe) he was ſomething iealous, yet had hee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any proofe of her inconſtancie: but he feared he was, or ſhould be a Cuckold, and therefore preuented it ſo much as he could by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining her libertie: but this did but ſet an edge to her wanton appetite, and was a prouocatiue to her Luſt (for what women are reſtrained from, they moſt deſire) for long hee could not hold his watchfull eye ouer her, 'cauſe his buſineſſe call'd him away, which alway lay farre from home. He being to depart from home, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought himſelfe what he were beſt to do: put another in truſt with his wife he durſt not: (for no greater ſhame is there to a man, then to be knowne iealous ouer his wife) himſelfe could tarry no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger at home for feare of loſing his place, and then his liuing was gone: thus was h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e troubled in minde, not knowing what to doe. Now he repented himſelfe that he had vſed his wife ſo ill, which had giuen her cauſe to hate him, and procure him a miſchiefe: for he ſaw that he had no other way now to take, but to put his credit into his w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es hands: therefore the day and night before hee went from home, he vſed her extraordinary kindely, making more on her then the firſt day they were married. His wife maruelled at this ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine change, and though ſhe liked this vſage well, yet ſhe thought neuer the better of him in her heart, and in her outward carriage bare her ſelfe as before: which was euer modeſtly in his ſight. The morning being come that he was to depart from home (after many ſwéet kiſſes, and kinde imbraces giuen by him) hee ſaid: Swéet honey, I cannot blame thee, that thou takeſt my vſage heretofore vnkindly: but if thou kneweſt (as I meane to ſhew thee) what my intent was, thou wilt change that bad thought for a better liking of me. Know then, my loue, that I vſed thee thus ſtrangely, to know how deepe thy loue was ſettled on me: (for to vſe a friend froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, tryes her loue, in forbearance of his iniuries: and in ſeeking to pleaſe him) which I haue found by proofe immoueable. Oh my more then deare wife, thy loue is fixed ſure on me, and not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued by any croſſe whatſoeuer. Thus did hee ſeeke to vnſnare
<pb facs="tcp:1998:6"/>
himſelfe, but was caught faſter: for his wife perceiuing his iealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, vowed to be reuenged, and giue him good and ſufficient cauſe to thinke himſelfe a Cuckold: and with very ioy to ſee him creepe to her after this manner, ſhe let fall a few teares, which proceeded ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of inward laughter, then any griefe. Hee ſeeing this, thought they proceeded from pure loue, yet did hee not thorowly truſt her, but minded to returne ere ſhe was aware of him. To be ſhort, they broke their faſts together, and louingly parted: His wife beeing glad of this, ſent for a woman in the towne, one that was the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curer of her friend, to whom ſhe told all that had hapned betweene her Huſband and her ſelfe: requeſting her in all haſte to giue her friend notice that her huſband was now from home, and that ſhee would meete him, when and whereſoeuer he pleaſed. The old wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man glad of this, gaue her Louer to vnderſtand of this good hap, who ſoone met her at a place in the towne, where they vſually met, where they plumed the Sumpter-mans Cap: there ſhe gaue the old Woman a key which would open her doore, by which meanes ſhee might come to the ſpeech of her at any time of the night without knocking: ſo carefull was ſhe to keepe her ſelfe cleere and ſpotleſſe in the eyes of her neighbours: who would not haue thought well of her, if they had heard noiſe at her doore in the night, and her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band from home; hauing paſſed the time away in louing comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they parted, each going their ſeuerall wayes: not any one of her neighbours miſtruſting her, ſhe bare her ſelfe ſo cunningly modeſt. Her huſband being on his iourny, following his Sumpter-horſe, thought his wife at home working like a good huſwife (when perchance ſhe was following a Stalion ſhe tooke more delight in, then he poore man did in his) yet put he no more truſt in her then he was forced to doe: for hee diſpatches his buſineſſe ſo ſoone as hee could, and returned three dayes ſooner then he promiſed her. When he came home he knocked at the doore: there might he knocke long inough for his Wife, who was knocking the Vintners pots with her Louer. He hauing no anſwere, began to curſe and ban, bidding a poxe on all Whores: his neighbours began to perſwade him, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him that ſhe went but new forth, &amp; would returne ſuddenly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: and iuſt at that inſtant came ſhe homeward, not knowing her good man was returned, for ſhe had appointed the old Woman to come and call her that night: Seeing her Huſband, you may iudge
<pb facs="tcp:1998:6"/>
what a taking this poore Woman was in: back ſhe durſt not goe for that would haue but ſharpened his rage: and if ſhee went for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſhe was ſure of ſome ſeuere puniſhment: yet taking cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, on ſhe went: Her huſband entertained her with halfe a doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen gadding Queans, and ſuch like words, &amp; ſhe excuſed her ſelfe ſo well as ſhe could But to be briefe, in a dores they went: then made he the doore faſt, and came to her (who was almoſt dead with feare that her cloſe play now would be deſcride) ſaying; Thou Whore, long time haue I doubted this looſenes in thy life, which I now haue plaine proofe of by thy gadding in my abſence, and doe thou at this preſent looke for no other thing at my hands, then reward fit for ſo vilde a creature as a Whore is. At theſe words ſhe would haue ſkreeked out: but he ſtopped her mouth, pulling withall a ruſty Dagger from his ſide, vowing to ſcowre it with her bloud, if ſhee did but offer to open her mouth. She poore creature forced more with feare, then with duty, held her peace, while hee bound her to a poſt hard by the dore, vowing ſhe ſhould ſtand there al night, to coole her hote bloud. Hauing done this, about ten of the clock he went to bed, telling her that he meant not to ſleepe, but watch her if ſhe durſt once open her mouth: but he was better then his word, though hee held it not, for he was no ſooner in bed but he foll faſt aſleepe, being wearied with riding. Long had not he beene ſo, but the old Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man came &amp; opened the dore with the key that the Sumpter-mans wife had giuen her, and was going to the bed which the Sumpter-man lay vpon, to call his Wife: but as ſhe paſſed by, the poore wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that was bound to her good behauiour, call'd her by her name (yet very ſoftly) ſaying, Mother <hi>Ione,</hi> I am héere, mother <hi>Ione,</hi> pray goe no furder, and ſpeake ſoftly: for my Huſband, mother <hi>Ione,</hi> is a bed. This good old Woman went to her, and finding her bound, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked her the cauſe: to whom the afflicted Wife related (with ſtill ſpeech, which is contrary to womens nature) euery circumſtance, for ſhe knew her Huſband faſt enough for three houres. Is that all, ſaid the old Woman? then feare not but you ſhal enioy your friends bed: with that ſhe vnlooſed her. The Sumpter-mans wife maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led what ſhe meant to doe, ſaying, Mother, what meane you? this is not the way that I muſt take to cléere my ſelfe. Alas, ſhould he wake and finde me gone to morrow he will kill mee in his rage. Content you, ſaid the old Wife, I will bide the brunt of all: and heere will
<pb facs="tcp:1998:7"/>
I ſtand tyed to this poſt till you returne, which I pray let be ſo ſoone as you can. This wanton Wife praiſed her counſell, and imbraces the ſame, and leauing the old Woman bound (as ſhe deſired) in her place, ſhe went to her luſty Louer, who long time had expected her: to whom ſhe related her huſbands vnluckie comming home, her ill vſage, and the old Womans kindneſſe: for all which he was ſorrie, but could not mend, onely hee promiſed to reward this kinde wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, call'd Mother <hi>Ione:</hi> ſo leauing that talke they fell to other.</p>
               <p>The Sumpter-man, who could not ſoundly ſleepe, becauſe ſtill he dreamed of Hornes and Cuckolds, wakened not long after his wife was gone: and being wakened, he fell to talking after this manner: Now you queane, is it good gadding? Is your hote bloud cooled yet with the cold ayre? Will your inſatiable deſires be allayed with hunger and cold? if they be not, thou arrant Whore, I will tye this thus vp, not onely nine dayes, but nineteene times nine dayes, till thou haſt loſt this hote and damnable pride of thine: Ile doo 't, Whore, I will, I ſweare I will. This good old Woman hearing him rayle thus frantickly, wiſhed (with all her heart) her ſelfe out of doores, and his Wife in her old place. Shee durſt not ſpeake to him, for feare ſhe ſhould be knowne by her ſpeech to bee another, and not his Wife: and hee lay ſtill calling to her, aſking if her hote deſires were cooled. At length hee hearing her make no anſwere, thought her to be ſullen: and bid her ſpeak to him, or elſe ſhe ſhould repent it: (yet durſt not the old wife ſpeake.) He hearing no ſpeech, roſe vp, and tooke his knife, ſwearing hee would marke her for a Whore, and with thoſe words he ranne to her, and cut her ouer the noſe: all this the old Woman indured quietly, knowing her words would haue but increaſed her puniſhment. To bed went he againe, with ſuch words as hee vſed before, ſaying, that ſince her bloud would not coole, he would let it out. Hauing lyen a while, he fell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe, leauing old <hi>Ione</hi> bleeding at noſe, where ſhee ſtood till three of the clocke in the morning: at which time this honeſt Laſſe (the Sumpter-mans wife) came home: when ſhe had quietly opened the doore, ſhe went to the old Woman, aſking her how ſhee had ſped? Marry, quoth ſhe, as I would wiſh my enemies to ſpeed, ill: I pray vnkinde me, or I ſhall bleed to death. The good wife was ſorry to heare that ſhe had receiued ſuch hurt, but farre gladder that it did not happen vnto her ſelfe: ſo vnbinding her, ſhe ſtood in her place.
<pb facs="tcp:1998:7"/>
Homeward went the old Woman, bethinking her ſelfe all the way how ſhe might excuſe that hurt to her Huſband: At laſt ſhe had one (for excuſes are neuer further off women then their apron ſtrings) which was this: ſhe went home to her huſband, who was a Maſon, and went euery morning betimes to worke out of the towne: him ſhe calleth, telling him it was time to goe to worke; the ſilly man roſe, and being ready to goe, he miſſed a Chiſell (which his wife had hid) and went vp and downe groping for it in the darke, praying his Wife to helpe him to looke it. She made as ſhe had ſought for it, but in ſtead of that, ſhe gaue him a ſharpe knife (which a Butcher had brought to grinding) he catching at this ſuddenly (as one being in haſte) cut all his fingers, ſo that with anger he threw the knife to the earth, curſing his Wife that gaue it him. Preſently vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fall of the knife, ſhe cryed out that ſhee was hurt. The Maſon being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, went and lighted a Candle, and returning, he found his wiues noſe cut. The ſilly man (perſwading himſelfe that hee had done it with hurling the knife) intreated her for to forgiue him, for he proteſted that hee thought her no hurt when hee did it: then fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched he a Surgeon who cunningly ſtitched it vp, that it was whole in a ſhort time. The Sumpter-man all this while did little thinke how he was beguiled: who when he was awaked, lighted a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to ſée what hurt he had done his Wife in his rage: he comming neere her, and ſeeing her face whole, ſtood in amaze, not knowing what to thinke on it, for he was ſure that he had cut her noſe. His Wife ſéeing him ſtand in this maner, aſked him what he did ayle, &amp; why he gazed ſo on her as though he knew her not? Pardon mee, Wife, quoth he, for this night hath a miracle beene wrought: I doe ſee plainely that the heauens will not ſuffer the Innocent to ſuffer harme. Then fetched hee his knife which was all bloudy, ſaying, Deare Wife, with this knife did I giue thee this preſent night, a wound on the face, the which moſt miraculouſly is whole: which is a ſigne thou art free, and ſpotleſſe, and ſo will I euer hold thee. His Wife ſaid little (for feare of laughing) onely ſhee ſaid, ſhe knew heauen would defend the Innocent: ſo they went to bed louingly together, he vowing neuer to thinke amiſſe on her. So had ſhe more libertie then before, &amp; the old had gold for her wound, which wound was ſo well cured (I thanke God) that you can ſcarce ſee it on my noſe. Hereat they all laughed, ſaying, ſhe had told a good Tale
<pb facs="tcp:1998:8"/>
for her ſelfe: at which ſhe bit her lip, to thinke how ſhe was ſo very a foole to betray her ſelfe. But knowing that excuſes would but make her more ſuſpected, ſhe held her tongue, giuing the next leaue to ſpeake.</p>
               <p>The next that ſate to her was a Fiſhwife of <hi>Standon</hi> the Gréene, who ſaid her Tale was pleaſant, but ſcarce honeſt: ſhee taxed wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with too much immodeſtie: to ſalue which, ſhe would tell the aduentures of a poore Gentlewoman, that was vſed vnkindly by her Huſband. They all liked this well, and intreated her to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede: which ſhe willingly conſented vnto.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="tale">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <head>The deſcription of the Fiſhwife of <hi>Standon</hi> the Greene.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This wife was leane,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Shee went full cleane.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her breath not ſtrong,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her body long.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She looked pale,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Yet lou'd good Ale.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her teeth were rot,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her tongue was not.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Well could ſhe chat</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Of this and that.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her lips were white,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And ſharpe her ſight.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her cheekes were thin,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>So was her chin,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And ſomething hook'd,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her noſe was crook'd:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>They would haue kiſt,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But that they wiſt,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her mouth was let,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That twixt was ſet.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Twice thirtie yeeres,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Sha'd paſt with cares,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And honeſt life,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And ſtill was Wife.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This Wife was wiſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But not preciſe:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thus gan ſhe tell:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pray marke it well.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <head>Her Tale.</head>
               <p>IN the troubleſome raigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, there dwelt in <hi>Waltam</hi> (not farre from London) a Gentleman, which had to Wife a creature moſt beautifull: ſo that in her time there were few found that matched her, (none at all that excelled her) ſo excellent were the gifts that nature had beſtowed on her. In body was ſhe not onely ſo rare, and vnparaleld, but alſo in her gifts of minde: ſo that in this creature it ſeemed, that Grace and Nature ſtroue who ſhould excell each other in their gifts toward her. The
<pb facs="tcp:1998:8"/>
Gentleman her Huſband thought himſelfe ſo happy in his choiſe, that he beleeued, in chooſing her, he had tooke hold of that bleſſing which heauen proffereth euery man once in his life. Long did not this opinion hold for currant; for in his height of loue, he began ſo to hate her, that he ſought her death: the cauſe I will tell you. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing buſineſſe one day to London, he tooke his leaue very kindly of his Wife, and accompanied with one man, he rode to London: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing toward night, he tooke vp his Inne, and to be briefe, he went to ſupper amongſt other Gentlemen. Amongſt other talke at table, one tooke occaſion to ſpeake of women, and what excellent crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures they were, ſo long as they continued loyall to man. To whom anſwered one, ſaying: This is truth, Sir: ſo is the Diuell good ſo long as he doth no harme, which is meaner: his goodnes and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens loyaltie will come both in one yeere, but it is ſo farre off, that none in this age ſhall liue to ſee it.</p>
               <p>This Gentleman louing his Wife dearely (and knowing her to be free from this vnciuill Gentlemans generall taxation of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) in her behalfe, ſaid: Sir, you are too bitter againſt the ſexe of women, and doe ill (for ſome ones ſake that hath proued falſe to you) to taxe the generalitie of women-kinde with lightneſſe: and but I would not be counted vnciuill amongſt theſe Gentlemen, I would giue you the reply that approued vntruth deſerueth, you know my meaning, Sir: conſtrue my words as you pleaſe: excuſe me, Gentlemen, if I be vnciuill: I anſwere in the behalfe of one, who is as free from diſloyaltie, as is the Sunne from darknes, or the fire from cold. Pray, Sir, ſaid the other, ſince wee are oppoſite in opinions, let vs rather talke like Lawyers, that wee may bee quickly friends againe, then like Souldiers which end their words with blowes. Perhaps this woman that you anſwere for, is chaſte, but yet againſt her will: for many women are honeſt, 'cauſe they haue not the meanes, and opportunitie to bee diſ-honeſt (ſo is a Thiefe true in priſon, 'cauſe he hath nothing to ſteale:) had I but opportunitie, and knew this ſame Saint you ſo adore, I would pawne my life and whole eſtate, in a ſhort while to bring you ſome manifeſt token of her diſloyaltie. Sir, you are yong in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of womens ſlights, your want of experience makes you too credulous: therefore be not abuſed. This ſpeech of his made the Gentleman more out of patience then before, ſo that with much
<pb facs="tcp:1998:9"/>
adoe he held himſelfe from offering violence: but his anger beeing a little ouer, hee ſaid, Sir, I doe verily beleeue, that this vaine ſpeech of yours proceedeth rather from a looſe and ill manner'd minde, then of any experience you haue had of womens looſenes: and ſince you thinke your ſelfe ſo cunning in that (diuelliſh art) of corrupting womens chaſtitie, I will lay downe heere a hundred pounds, againſt which you ſhall lay fifty pounds, and before theſe Gentlemen I promiſe you, if that within a moneths ſpace you bring me any token of this Gentlewomans diſloyaltie (for whoſe ſake I haue ſpoken in the behalfe of all women) I doe freely giue you leaue to inioy the ſame: conditionally you not performing it, I may enioy your money. If that it be a match, ſpeake, and I will acquaint you where ſhe dwelleth: and beſides, I bow, as I am a Gentleman, not to giue her notice of any ſuch intent that is toward her. Sir, quoth the man, your proffer is faire, and I accept the ſame: ſo the mony was deliuered into the Oaſt of the houſe his hands, and the ſitters by were witneſſes: ſo drinking together like friends, they went euery man to his chamber. The next day this man hauing knowledge of the place, rid thither, leauing the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man at the Inne, who being aſſured of his wiues chaſtitie, made no of her account but to winne the wager, but it fell out otherwiſe: for the other vowed either by force, policie, or free will to get ſome Iewell or other toy from her, which was enough to perſwade the Gentleman that he was a Cuckold, and win the wager he had laid. This Villaine (for hee deſerued no better ſtile) lay at Waltam a whole day, before he came to the ſight of her: at laſt he eſpyed her in the fields, to whom he went and kiſſed her (a thing no modeſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man can deny:) after his ſalutation, he ſaid, Gentlewoman, I pray pardon me if I haue beene too hold, I was intreated by your Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band which is at London (I riding this way) to come and fée you, by me he hath ſent his commends to you, with a kinde intreat that you would not be diſcontented for his long abſence, it being ſerious buſineſſe that keepes him from your ſight. The Gentlewoman ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry modeſtly bade him welcome, thanking him for his kindnes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all telling him that her Huſband might command her patience ſo long as he pleaſed. Then intreated ſhee him to walke homeward, where ſhee gaue him ſuch entertainment as was fit for a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and her huſbands friend. In the time of his abiding at her
<pb facs="tcp:1998:9"/>
houſe, he oft would haue ſingled her in priuate talke, but ſhe percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the ſame, (knowing it to bee a thing not fitting a modeſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) would neuer come in his ſight but at meales, and then were there ſo many at boord, that it was no time for to talke of lone mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: therefore hee ſaw hee muſt accompliſh his deſire ſome other way: which he did in this maner: He hauing layne two nights at her houſe, and perceiuing her to bee free from luſtfull deſires, the third night he fained himſelfe to be ſomething ill, and ſo went to bed timelier then he was wont. When he was alone in his chamber, he began to think with himſelfe that it was now time to do that which he determined; for if he tarried any longer, they might haue cauſe to think that he came for ſome ill intent, and waited opportunity to execute the ſame therefore he reſolued to doe ſomething that night, that might winne him the wager, or vtterly bring him in deſpaire of the ſame. With this reſolution he went to her chamber, which was but a paire of ſtaires from his, and finding the doore open, her went in, placing himſelf vnder the bed: Long had he not lyne there, but in came the Gentlewoman with her maiden; who hauing béen at prayers with her houſhold, was going to bed. She preparing her ſelfe to bedward, laid her Head-tyre &amp; thoſe Iewels ſhe wore, on a little table there by: at length hee perceiued her to put off a littel Crucifix of gold, which dayly ſhe wore next to her heart: this Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well he thought fitteſt for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne, and therefore obſerued where ſhe did lay the ſame: At length the Gentlewoman hauing vntyred her ſelfe, went to bed: her Maid then bolting of the doore, tooke the Candle, and went to bed in a withdrawing roome onely ſeparated with Arras. This Villaine lay ſtill vnder the bed, liſtning if hee could heare that the Gentlewoman ſlept: at length he might heare her draw her breath long: then thought hee all ſure, and like a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning villains roſe without noiſe, going ſtraight to the Table, where finding of the Crucifix, he lightly went to the doore, which he cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly vnbolted; all this performed he with ſo little noiſe, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Miſtris nor the Maid heard him. Hauing gotten into his Chamber, he wiſhed for day, that he might carry this Iewell to her huſband as ſigne of his wiues diſloyaltie: but ſeeing his wiſhes but in vaine, he laid him downe to ſleepe: happy had ſhee beene had his bed proued his graue. In the morning ſo ſoone as the folkes were ſtirring, he roſe and went to the Horſe-keeper, praying him to
<pb facs="tcp:1998:10"/>
helpe him to his Horſe, telling him that hee had tooke his leaue of his Miſtris the laſt night. Mounting his horſe, away rid he to Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, leauing the Gentlewoman in bed: who when ſhe roſe, attiring her ſelfe haſtity ('cauſe one tarried to ſpeake with her) miſſed not her Crucifix: ſo paſſed ſhe the time away, as ſhee was wont other dayes to doe, no whit troubled in minde, though much ſorrow was toward her: onely ſhee ſeemed a little diſcontented that her gheſt went away ſo vnmannerly, ſhe vſing him ſo kindely. So leauing her, I will ſpeake of him, who the next morning was betimes at London; and comming to the Inne, hee aſked for the Gentleman, who then was in bed, but he quickly roſe and came downe to him, who ſeeing him return'd ſo ſuddenly, he thought hee came to haue leaue to releaſe himſelfe of his wager: but this chanced otherwiſe: for hauing ſaluted him, he ſaid in this manner: Sir, did not I tell you that you were too yong in experience of womans ſubtilties, and that no woman was longer good then ſhe had cauſe, or time to doe ill? this you beleeued not, and thought it a thing ſo vnlikely, that you haue giuen me a hundred pounds for the knowledge of it. In briefe, know, your Wife is a woman, and therefore a wanton, a changeling: to confirme that I ſpeake, ſée heere (ſhewing him the Crucifix:) know you this? if this be not ſufficient proofe, I wil fetch you more.</p>
               <p>At the ſight of this, his bloud left his face, running to comfort his faint heart, which was ready to breake at the ſight of this Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifix, which he knew ſhe alwayes wore next her heart, and therefore he muſt (as he thought) goe ſomething neere, which ſtole ſo priuate a Iewell. But remembring himſelfe, he cheeres his ſpirits, ſeeing that was ſufficient proofe, and he had wonne the wager, which hee commanded ſhould be giuen to him. Thus was the poore Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman abuſed, who went into his Chamber, and beeing weary of this world (ſeeing where he had put onely his truſt, he was decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues) he was minded to fall vpon his ſword, and ſo end all his miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries at once: but his better <hi>Genius</hi> perſwaded him contrary, and not ſo (by laying violent hand on himſelfe) to leape into the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels mouth. Thus being in many mindes, but reſoluing no one thing, at laſt he concluded to puniſh her with death, which had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued his truſt, and himſelfe vtterly to forſake his houſe and lands, and follow the fortunes of King <hi>Henry.</hi> To this intent he
<pb facs="tcp:1998:10"/>
called his man, to whom he ſaid; <hi>George,</hi> thou knoweſt I haue euer held thee deare, making more account of thee, then thy other fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, and thou haſt often told me that thou diddeſt owe thy life to me, which at any time thou wouldeſt bee ready to render vp to doe me good. True Sir, (anſwered his man) I ſaid no more thne, then I will now at any time, whenſoeuer you pleaſe, performe. I beleeue thée, <hi>George</hi> (replyed he:) but there is no ſuch need: I onely would haue thee doe a thing for me, in which is no great danger, yet the profit which thou ſhalt haue thereby ſhall amount to my wealth: for the loue that thou beareſt to me, and for thy own good wilt thou do this? Sir (anſwered <hi>George</hi>) more for your loue, then any reward, I will doe it, (and yet money makes many men valiant) pray tell mee what it is? <hi>George</hi> (ſaid his Maſter) this it is, thou muſt goe home, praying thy Miſtris to meete me halfe the way to Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: but hauing her by the way, in ſome priuate place kill her: I meane as I ſpeake, kill her, I ſay, this is my command, which thou haſt promiſed to performe: which if thou performeſt not, I vow to kill thee the next time thou commeſt in my ſight. Now for thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward it ſhall be this, Take my Ring, and when thou haſt done my command: by vertue of it, doe thou aſſume my place till my returne, at which time thou ſhalt know what my reward is, till then gouern my whole eſtate: and for thy Miſtris abſence, &amp; my own, make what excuſe thou pleaſe: ſo be gone. Well Sir (ſaid <hi>George</hi>) ſince it is your will, though vnwilling I am to doe it, yet I will performe it. So went he his way toward Waltam: and his Maſter preſently rid to the Court, where hee abode with King <hi>Henry,</hi> who a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was inlarged by the Earle of Warwicke, and placed in the Throne againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George</hi> beeing come to Waltam, did his dutie to his Miſtris, who wondred to ſee him, and not her huſband, for whom ſhe deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of <hi>George:</hi> he anſwered her, that hee was at Enfield, and did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt her to meet him there. To which ſhee willingly agreed, and preſently rode with him toward Enfield. At length they being come into a by way, <hi>George</hi> began to ſpeake to her in this manner, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris, I pray you tel me what that Wife deſerues, who through ſome lewd behauiour of hers, hath made her Huſband to neglect his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and meanes of life, ſeeking by all meanes to dye, that he might be free from the ſhame, which her wickedneſſe hath purchaſed him?
<pb facs="tcp:1998:11"/>
Why <hi>George</hi> (quoth ſhee) haſt thou met with ſome ſuch creature? Be it whomſoeuer, might I be her Iudge, I thinke her worthy of death: How thinkeſt thou? Faith, Miſtris (ſaid he) I thinke ſo too, and am ſo fully perſwaded that her offence deſerueth that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, that I purpoſe to bee executioner to ſuch a one my ſelfe. Miſtris, you are this woman, you haue ſo offended my Maſter (you know beſt how your ſelfe) that he hath left his houſe, vowing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to ſee the ſame till you be dead, and I am the man appointed by him to kill you; therefore thoſe words which you meane to vtter, ſpeake them preſently, for I cannot ſtay. Poore Gentlewoman, at the report of theſe vnkinde words (ill deſerued at her hands) ſhe loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked as one dead, and vttering aboundance of teares, ſhe at laſt ſpake theſe words: And can it be, that my kindnes and louing obedience, hath merited no other reward at his hands then death? It cannot be. I know thou onely tryeſt me, how patiently I would endure ſuch an vniuſt command. I'le tell thée héere, thus with body pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate on the earth, and hands lift vp to heauen, I would pray for his preſeruation, thoſe ſhould be my worſt words: for deaths fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full viſage ſhewes pleaſant to that ſoule that is innocent. Why then prepare your ſelfe (ſaid <hi>George:</hi>) for by heauen I doe not reſt. With that ſhee prayed him ſtay, ſaying, And is if ſo; then what ſhould I deſire to liue, hauing loſt his fauour (and without offence) whom I ſe dearely loued, and in whoſe ſight my happineſſe did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt? come, let me die. Yet, <hi>George,</hi> let mee haue ſo much fauour at thy hands, as to commend me in theſe few words to him: Tell him, my death I willingly imbrace, for I haue owed him my life (yet no otherwiſe but by a wiues obedience) euer ſince I call'd him Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band: but that I am guilty of the leaſt fault toward him, I vtterly deny: and doe (at this houre of my death) deſire that heauen would powre down vengeance vpon me, if euer I offended him in thought. Intreat him that he would not ſpeake ought that were ill on mee, when I am dead, for in good troth I haue deſerued none. Pray hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen bleſſe him, I am prepared now ſtrike prethée home, and kill me and my griefes at once.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George</hi> ſéeing this, could not withhold himſelfe from ſhedding teares, and with pitie he let fall his ſword, ſaying: Miſtris, that I haue vſed you ſo roughly, pray pardon me, for I was commanded to by my Maſter, who hath vowed, if I let you liue, to kill me: But
<pb facs="tcp:1998:11"/>
I being perſwaded, that you are innocent, I will rather vndergoe the danger of his wrath, then to ſtaine my hands with the bloud of your cléere and ſpotleſſe breſt: Yet let mee intreat you (ſo much) that you would not come in his ſight (leſt in his rage he turne your butcher) but liue in ſome diſguiſe till time haue opened the cauſe of his miſtruſt, and ſhewed you guiltleſſe, which (I hope) will not belong.</p>
               <p>To this ſhe willingly granted (being loth to die cauſeleſſe) and thanked him for his kindnes; ſo parted they both, hauing teares in their eyes. <hi>George</hi> want home, where he ſhewed his Maſters King for the gouernment of the houſe, till his Maſter and Miſtris re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, which he ſaid liued a while at London, 'cauſe the time was ſo troubleſome, and that was a place where they were more ſecure then in the Countrey. This his fellowes beléeued, and were obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to his will, amongſt whom hee vſed himſelfe ſo kindely, that he had all their loues. This poore Gentlewoman (Miſtris of the houſe) in ſhort time got mans apparell for her diſguiſe; ſo wandred ſhe vp and downe the countrey, for ſhe could get no ſeruice, becauſe the time was ſo dangerous, that no man knew whom hee might truſt; onely ſhe maintained her ſelfe with the price of thoſe Iewels which ſhe had, all which ſhe ſold. At the laſt, being quite out of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and hauing nothing left (which ſhe could well ſpare) to make money of, ſhe reſolued rather to ſtarue, then ſo much to debate her ſelfe to become a begger: with this reſolution ſhe went to a ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place beſide Yorke, where ſhée liued the ſpace of two dayes on Hearbs, and ſuch things as ſhe could there finde. In this time it chanced that King <hi>Edward</hi> (béeing come out of <hi>France,</hi> and lying thereabout with the ſmall forces hée had) came that way with ſome two or thrée Noble men, with an intent to diſcouer, if any ambuſhes were laid to take him at an aduantage. He ſéeing there this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, whom he ſuppoſed to be a Boy, aſked her what ſhe was, &amp; what ſhe made there in that priuat place? To whom ſhée very wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and modeſtly withall anſwered, that ſhe was a poore Boy, whoſe bringing vp had bin better then her outward parts then ſhewed, but at that time ſhe was both friendleſſe, &amp; comfortleſſe, by reaſon of the late warre. He being moued, to ſée one ſo well featur'd (as ſhe was) to want, entertained her for one of his Pages, to whom ſhe ſhewed her ſelfe ſo dutifull, and louing, that (in ſhort time) ſhee had his loue
<pb facs="tcp:1998:12"/>
aboue all her fellows. Still followed ſhe the fortunes of K. <hi>Edward,</hi> hoping at laſt (as not long after it did fall out) to be reconciled to her huſband. After the battell at <hi>Barnet</hi> (where K. <hi>Edward</hi> got the beſt) ſhe going vp &amp; down amongſt the ſlaine men (to know whether her huſband, which was on K. <hi>Henries</hi> ſide, were dead or eſcaped) happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſée the other who had béen her gheſt, lying there for dead: ſhe remembring him, and thinking him to be one whom her huſband lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, went to him, &amp; finding him not dead, ſhe cauſed one to helpe her with him to a houſe there-by: where opening of his breſt, to dreſſe his wounds, ſhe eſpied her Crucifix; at ſight of which her heart was ioyfull (hoping by this, to find him that was the originall of her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace) for ſhe remembring her ſelfe, found that ſhe had loſt that Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix, euer ſince that morning he departed from her houſe ſo ſuddenly: But ſaying nothing of it at that time, ſhe cauſed him to be carefully looked vnto, and brought vp to London after her, whither ſhe want with the King, carrying the Crucifix with her. On a time when hée was a little recouered, ſhee went to him, giuing him the Crucifix, which ſhee had taken from about his necke: to whom hee ſaid, Good gentle Youth, kéep the ſame: for now in my miſery of ſicknes, when the ſight of that picture ſhould be moſt comfortable, it is to me moſt vncomfortable, and bréedeth ſuch horrour in my conſcience (when I think how wrongfully I got the ſame) that ſo long as I ſée it, I ſhall neuer be in reſt. Now knew ſhe that he was the man that cauſed the ſeparation twixt her huſband, and her ſelfe; yet ſaid ſhée nothing, vſing him as reſpectiuely as ſhe had before: only ſhe cauſed the man, in whoſe houſe he lay, to remember the words he had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken concerning the Crucifix. Not long after, ſhe being alone, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on the King, beſéeched his Grace to doe her iuſtice on a villain that had bin the cauſe of all the miſery ſhe had ſuffered. He louing her (aboue all his other Pages) moſt dearely, ſaid; <hi>Edmund</hi> (for ſo had ſhe named her ſelfe) thou ſhalt haue what right thou wilt on thy enemy; cauſe him to be ſent for, &amp; I will be thy Iudge my ſelfe. She being glad of this (with the Kings authority) ſent for her huſband, whom ſhe heard was one of the priſoners that was taken at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell of <hi>Barnet,</hi> ſhe appointing the other, now recouered, to be at the Court the ſame time. They being both come (but not one ſéeing of the other) the King ſent for the wounded man into the Preſence: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom the Page aſked him, how he came by the Crucifix? He
<pb facs="tcp:1998:12"/>
fearing that his Villany would come forth, denyed the words hée had ſaid before his Oaſt, affirming he bought it. With that ſhe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Oaſt of the houſe where he lay, bidding him boldly ſpeake what he had heard this man ſay, concerning the Crucifix. The Oaſt then told the King, that in the preſence of this Page, he heard him intreat, that the Crucifix might be taken from his ſight, for it did wound his conſcience, to thinke how wrongfully he had gotten the ſame. Theſe words did the Page auerre: yet he vtterly denyed the ſame, affirming that he bought it, and if that he did ſpeake ſuch words in his ſickneſſe, they proceeded from the lightneſſe of his braine, and were vntruthes.</p>
               <p>She ſeeing this Villains impudency, ſent for her Huſband in, to whom ſhe ſhewed the Crucifix, ſaying, Sir, doe you know, doe you know this? Yes, anſwered hee: but would God I ne're had knowne the owner of it? It was my Wiues, a woman vertuous, till this Diuell (ſpeaking to the other) did corrupt her purity, who brought me this Crucifix as a token of her inconſtancie.</p>
               <p>With that, the King ſaid, Sirra, now are you found to be a knaue: did you not euen now affirme you bought it? To whom he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (with fearefull countenance) And it like your Grace, I ſaid ſo, to preſerue this Gentlemans honour, and his Wiues, which by my telling of the truth would haue beene much indamag'd: for indéed ſhe being a ſecret friend of mine, gaue me this, as a teſtimony of her loue.</p>
               <p>The Gentlewoman, not being able longer to couer her ſelfe in that diſguiſe, ſaid, And it like your Maieſty, giue mee leaue to ſpeake, and you ſhall ſeeme make this Villaine confeſſe, how hee hath abuſed that good Gentleman. The King hauing giuen her leaue, ſhe ſaid, Firſt, Sir, you confeſſed before your Oaſt, and my ſelfe, that you had wrongfully got this Iewell: then before his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, you affirmed you bought it: ſo denying your former words: Now you haue denyed, that which you ſo boldly affirmed before, and haue ſaid it was this Gentlemans wiues gift. (With his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties leaue) I ſay thou art a Villaine, and this is likewiſe falſe: (with that ſhe diſcouered her ſelfe to be a woman, ſaying) Hadſt thou (Villaine) euer any Strumpets fauour at my hands? Did I (for any ſinfull pleaſure I receiued from thee) beſtow this on thée? Speake, and if thou haue any goodnes left in thée, ſpeake the truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1998:13"/>With that he being daunted at her ſudden ſight, fell on his knées before the King, beſéeching his Grace to be mercifull vnto him, for he had wronged that Gentlewoman: therewith told he the King of the match betweene the Gentleman and himſelfe, and how he ſtole the Crucifix from her, and by that meanes, perſwaded her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band that ſhe was a Whore. The King wondred how hee durſt (knowing God to bee iuſt) commit ſo great Villany: but much more admired he, to ſée his Page to turn a Gentlewoman; but cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to admire, he ſaid: Sir, (ſpeaking to her Huſband) you did the part of an vnwiſe man, to lay ſo fooliſh a wager, for which offence, the remembrance of your folly is puniſhment inough: but ſeeing it concernes me not, your Wife ſhall be your Iudge. With that Miſtris <hi>Dorrill</hi> (thanking his Maieſtie) went to her Huſband, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Sir, all my anger to you I lay downe with this kiſſe. He won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring all this while to ſee this ſtrange and vnlooked for change, wept for ioy, deſiring her to tell him how ſhe was preſerued: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhe ſatiſfied him at full. The King was likewiſe glad that hee had preſerued this Gentlewoman from wilfull familie, and gaue Iudgement on the other in this manner: That he ſhould reſtore the money treble which he had wrongfully got from him: and ſo was to haue a yeeres impriſonment. So this Gentleman and his Wife went (with the Kings leaue) louingly home, where they were kindely welcomed by <hi>George,</hi> to whom for recompence hee gaue the money which he receiued: ſo liued they euer after in great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. How like you of this woman? Some praiſed her (as ſhee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued) extraordinarily.</p>
               <p>But (ſaid the <hi>Brainford</hi> Fiſhwife) I like her as a garment out of faſhion; ſhee ſhewed well in that innocent time, when women had not the wit to know their owne libertie: but if ſhe liued now, ſhe would ſhew as vild as a paire of Yorkeſhire ſleeues in a Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmithes ſhop.</p>
               <p>But wee being come almoſt at <hi>Brainford,</hi> I aſked if any of them would land there? They all cryed, No: perſwading the two wiues that dwelt at <hi>Brainford,</hi> and <hi>Standon</hi> the Greene, to goe to <hi>King-ſtone,</hi> whither they purpoſed all to goe and be merry. Little intreating ſerued them: ſo putting their Fiſh-baſkets aboord a Fiſher-boate, they cryed, On to <hi>King-ſtone.</hi> I being well content therewith, ſet forward, and the Fiſhwife of <hi>Richmond</hi> proceeded
<pb facs="tcp:1998:13"/>
in telling of her Tale: but firſt I will tell you what manner of creature ſhe was.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="tale">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <head>The Fiſhwife of <hi>Richmond.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This <hi>Richmond</hi> Dame</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Was voyd of ſhame,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She was a ſcold</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>At ten yeeres old:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And now was held</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The beſt in field,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>At that ſame fight</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>'T was her delighs.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her Husband kinde</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>(A ſilly Hinde)</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Durſt not gainſay</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Or once ſay nay,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For what ſhe crau'd:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For then ſhe rau'd</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And call'd him foole,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And with a ſtoole</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Would breake his head.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Oft in the bed</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If he her tutch'd,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>His Beard ſhe clutch'd,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And claw'd his eyes:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Yet in no wiſe</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Durſt he reſiſt</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her cruell fiſt.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This Wife was yong:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Onely in tongue</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She was deform'd:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Had that beene charm'd:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She had deſeru'd</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A King to ha' ſeru'd.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <head>Her Tale.</head>
               <p>NOt long agone, in a towne not farre from London, dwelt an old Widdower, which tooke to Wife a faire, yong and luſty Damozell, ouer whom his owne weakeneſſe made him iealous, ſo that continually his eye was on her, and ſhe could not looke away, but with moſt ſpitefull words he would reuile her, calling her ſo many Whores, that it was vnpoſſible to make him ſo many times Cuckold: This poore wench liued ſo miſerable a life with him, that ſhe rather wiſhed to be with the dead, then to liue with ſo froward, and ſuch a doting old foole: but her wiſhes were in vaine, and her miſery ſtill increaſed: For he complained to her friends, how that ſhe ſhewed not that dutie to him, which other Wiues did to their Huſbands, but flighted him as if he had beene a ſtranger, and that ſhee delighted in other mens companies more then his.</p>
               <p>Vpon this complaint of his, ſhee had likewiſe the ill will of her
<pb facs="tcp:1998:14"/>
friends, who told her they would continue her foes, till they heard ſhe vſed her Huſband with more reſpect. At this ſhee grieued more, then at her Huſbands frowardnes, hauing their hate with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a cauſe: and being one day at Church ſhe made mone to her Pew-fellow (which was a wench that would not be out-faced by her Huſbands great lookes) telling her how ill her Huſband vſed her, for when hee was within doores, his eyes were neuer off her, ſo that ſhe could not ſpeake to any friend: and if he went forth, he would locke her in the houſe like Puſſe-Cat; and euery night he locked the doore himſelfe, laying the key vnder his pillow. Why, ſaid her Pew-fellow, wherfore haue you hands, but to take the key when hee is aſléepe, and to goe whither you will, onely you muſt be carefull to come in at the houre he vſeth to wake? Fie, I am aſhamed, that you haue no more wit: doe as I tell you, and ſince he barreth you of your libertie in the day, take it your ſelfe in the night: for company take no care, come to me; and if wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not finde ſport to paſſe away the time, wee will ſleepe for company.</p>
               <p>This yong Laſſe thanked her for her counſell, vowing to put it in practice the next night what ſoeuer did happen: ſo returning from the Church with her huſband, ſhe went home, where all the day ſhe ſate demurely in his ſight, as ſhe was wont to doe, yet could ſhée ſcarce haue one good word from him.</p>
               <p>Night being come, he locked the doore as he was wont, &amp; going to bed, he layed the key vnder his pillow, falling quickly aſleep, which ſhe perceiuing, ſoftly tooke the ſame, opening the doore therewith: away ſhe went to her Pew-fellow, where ſhe reuelled that night, till three of the clocke in the morning, at which time her Huſband vſed to wake: then comming home, ſhe ſoftly opened the doore, locking the ſame againe with as little noiſe as ſhe could: then laid ſhe her ſelfe downe by her good man, who when he waked, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer miſtruſted that his Wife had ſtirred from his ſide: This did ſhee many times, and neuer was ſo much as ſuſpected for ſuch a matter.</p>
               <p>One night aboue the reſt (her good fortune hauing made her bold) ſhe tarrying a little longer then her houre, her Huſband chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to awake; who preſently miſſing her, call'd her by her name, thinking ſhe had beene in the houſe: he hearing no anſwere, roſe and went about the houſe to looke her, but he could not ſet his eyes
<pb facs="tcp:1998:14"/>
on her, and to aſke for her was in vaine, for his Cat could not ſpeake, and he had no other to inquire of: for his Cat, his Wife, and himſelfe, was all the houſhold he had.</p>
               <p>To bed went this old man againe, where hee looked for the key, but could finde none: there he lay, vexing and chafing himſelfe, euer and anon féeling on his browes, which he perſwaded himſelfe were in their Spring-time, and would ſhortly bring forth fruit: though the reſt of his body were in Autumne. At length he might heare a noiſe, and lying ſtill, he might perceiue his Wife come ſtealing to the bed, to whom hee ſaid nothing, hoping one night to take her out of the doores, where hee would keepe her to her euerlaſting ſhame, and giue the Pariſh notice of her night-walking: ſo taking no notice that he knew any thing, he vſed her that day very kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which made her to beleeue that the Prouerbe is true (Cuckolds are kinde men) for before ſhe played looſe with him, ſhe neuer had that good vſage at his hand, as ſhe had that day found.</p>
               <p>This encouraged her to goe on in theſe her mad prankes, ſo that the ſame night ſhe purpoſed to walke againe, which ſhe did, taking the key from vnder his pillow (as ſhe was wont to doe) ſhe vnlocked the doore, and away ſhe went to her Pew-fellow: hee perceiuing it (for he ſlept For ſleepe) went downe, and bolted the doore after her, ſo that ſhe could not come in, but he muſt know of it: when he had ſo done, he layd him downe to ſleepe.</p>
               <p>His Wife ending her Reuels, at her vſuall houre, returned home, and very quietly aſſayed to open the doore: but perceiuing that it was bol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed on the inſide, her heart was dead (as a ſpent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digals, at the ſight of a Sergeant:) then repented ſhee that ſhe had taken that wanton courſe, knowing a ſeuere puniſhment would follow her ſweet pleaſure: Thus ſhee, poore ſoule, ſtood at the doore ſhaking with feare, more then cold: but at laſt (hauing no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way to get in) ſhe reſolued to knocke: ſo laying her hand gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly on the ring of the doore, ſhe knocked twiſe or thriſe before hee would heare her. At laſt, hee looked out of the window, aſking who knockt at the doore? Tis I, kinde Huſband, (anſwered ſhee) that haue beene at a womans labour; prethée ſweet heart open the doore. All theſe kinde words would not get her admittance, but gained this churliſh anſwere at his hands: Haſt thou beene at a womans labour? Then prethee ſweet heart returne, and amongſt
<pb facs="tcp:1998:15"/>
the reſidue of the wiues, help thou to deuoure the groning Cheeſs, and ſucke vp the honeſt mans Ale till you are drunke, by that time 'twill be day-light, and I will haue thy friends at thy returne, who ſhall giue thée thankes for thy charitie.</p>
               <p>The poore woman knew his wicked mind toward her; by theſe his mocking words, yet ſought ſhe to pacifie the ſame; ſaying, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, kinde Loue, theſe things are done already; therefore pray o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the doore? No (quoth he) auaunt Whore; damn'd Whore, auaunt. Heere is no place, your labours haue not deſerued ſuch fruits at my hands: No, I haue taken you, you are intrapt, you are ſnared, your friends ſhall now know, and all the world ſée, that you are a moſt cunning Whore: therefore reſt quiet, for there you ſhall ſtand till morning.</p>
               <p>This ſharpe anſwere of his kild her heart; but ſhe quickly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiued the ſame with a tricke which ſhe hoped would get her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance, which ſhe put in execution after this manner: Am I rewarded thus (quoth ſhe) for my charitie toward a poore diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed woman? and is this thy thankes thou giueſt mee for all my care which I haue had of thy old and crazed carkaſſe? I ſee it is, therefore will I liue no longer, but preſently will make away my ſelfe, and with my ſelfe thee, for the world iudging thee to bee author of my death, will giue thee the puniſhment that is due vnto a murderer.</p>
               <p>At this the old man laughed, bidding her proceed. Which ſhe hearing, tooke vp a great ſtone, going therewith to a Pond which was within a yards length of her houſe, and ſtanding at the brink, ſaid theſe words: Oh bleſſed element of water, it is thou which waſt ordained to end my miſery, and to reuenge me on my wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked huſband: therewith hurled ſhe in the ſtone which made a great noiſe: then placed ſhee her ſelfe hard by the doore. Her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band thinking ſhee had leaped in, and conſidering what danger hee might come in if ſhee was drowned, ranne haſtily out of doore to helpe her: which his Wife ſeeing, ſtept in, bolting of him forth.</p>
               <p>The old man ſtood a long time looking with his Spectacles on the Pond: but perceiuing nothing to ſtirre, hee thought her to be drowned, and with that cryed out he was vndone. Long inough might he cry, for no neighbours dwelt neere him: at length his
<pb facs="tcp:1998:15"/>
Wife pittied him, ſaying, Alas, good man, what wouldſt thou haue? He hearing it to be his wiues voice, was glad thereof: yet continuing his churliſh ſpeeches vnto her, he bid her open the doore, calling her diſſembling Queane.</p>
               <p>To all this ſaid ſhe nothing: but at laſt ſhee tooke occaſion to emptie the Piſ-pot on his head, and then ſaid, There is ſome Cuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kolds Vrine to coole your tongues heat; I'le warrant thee it is right, 'tis of my Huſbands making: ſo prethee, fellow, bee gone and let me ſleepe.</p>
               <p>This abuſe of hers, made the old man to raile more then before: but at laſt, ſéeing he could get nothing thereby, thee gaue her good words, intreating her to let him in, and hee would forgiue all that was paſt, neuer letting her friends vnderſtand of her night-wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</p>
               <p>She ſeeing him ſo meeke, ſaid, Old man, I could well afford thee ſhelter in my houſe, though thou haſt not deſerued the ſame: but in ſo doing I ſhall breake my oath, for I haue ſworne that thou ſhalt not come through the doore not this fiue houres: now to ſaue my oath, and doe thee pleaſure (in taking thee out of the cold) I will open the window in the lower roome, that thou mayſt come in that way. Her huſband being glad any way to get out of the cold, than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked her for that kindnes.</p>
               <p>Downe came ſhe ſtraight and opened that window: the old man glad thereof, thruſt in his head, praying her to helpe him. She now thinking it time to bee reuenged on him, tooke hold of his Beard, and with her other fiſt batterd his face, and ſcratched him in ſuch pitious manner, that the old man thought ſhee would haue killed him: and therfore pulling his head out of the window, he all be bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the Caſements with ſtones, calling her a hundred Whores.</p>
               <p>At this ſhe laughed, and bid him bee a patient Cuckold, for his greateſt miſery was to come; ſo going to a backe window, ſhee eſpyed a Boy, whom ſhe called, willing him to goe to ſuch a ones houſe (naming her Pew-fellow) and intreat her ſtraight to come and ſpeake with her. The Boy doing her errand, her Pew-fellow came: to whom ſhee told (not without great laughing) the whole ſtory of her good hap; willing her to goe to her Mother, and the reſt of her friends, and (as ſhe could well inough without her inſtructions) frame a complaint, how that her Huſband of a
<pb facs="tcp:1998:16"/>
long time had vſed to goe on whore hunting in the night: yet ſhee hauing no iuſt proofe of the ſame, was loth to ſpeake: but now it was her hap to take him forth of the doores, where ſhe would keep him, till they came to take ſome order that ſhe might bee ſeparated from him, for ſhe feared her life.</p>
               <p>With this Tale ranne her Pew-fellow to her friends (which dwelled not farre off) to whom ſhe told ſuch a pitious ſtory) of the miſerable life their poore kinſwoman led, with that knowne and proued old adulterer; that her friends moued with the wrong ſhe ſuſtained, got the Parſon of the towne to goe with them to their Kinſwomans houſe, that hee might be a witneſſe of her wrong.</p>
               <p>When they came thither, they found the old man ſitting at the doore, with a face more deformed (with beating and ſcratching) then euer was any Witches. The Mother to this luſty Laſſe, ſéeing him ſit there with ſuch a deformed face, raiſed her voice to a high key, ſaying: Ah, thou old Knaue, thou Whore monger, thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepit Lecher, Haſt thou alwayes complained of my Daughter, making mee, and other that are her good friends (not onely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue her, but more which I ſpeake to my griefe) to hate her, for her neglect of dutie toward thee, when the fault was in thy ſelfe, when thou gaueſt her right to others? but ſee, now it is come home by thee, ſhee hath intrapt thee in thy ſnare; then art come home with thy face mangled like a true Ruffian: now thou art the true Picture of a brothell-houſe companion: thou haſt the Seales on thy face, which thoſe creatures (called Whores) doe giue: thou haſt, villaine, thou haſt.</p>
               <p>He wondring to ſee her Mother ſo againſt him, of whom he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to be righted, ſaid: Mother, I confeſſe, theſe ſeales are the ſeales of a Whore; but of what Whore? Euen of what whore thou wilt (quoth ſhe:) thou knaue, hold thy tongue, confeſſe not heere, keepe that for the gallowes. Beare witneſſe, good <hi>Sir Iohn,</hi> and the reſt of my neighbours, that ſee how my daughter is abuſed: for I purpoſe to teach this knaue how to vſe his wife better; and not to abuſe her, and then threaten her with death, if ſhe complaine: come downe my child and ſpeake for thy ſelfe, and let the knaue touch thee if he dare.</p>
               <p>The yong Wife liked this well, who came downe as her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bid her; &amp; falling at her feet, intreated her (with fained teares)
<pb facs="tcp:1998:16"/>
that ſhe might be diuorced from her wicked huſband, or elſe ſhee ſaid her dayes were but ſhort, for he aſſuredly would doe her a miſchiefe.</p>
               <p>Content thee, Daughter (ſaid her Mother) I will haue him conſent to let thee goe, giuing thee that portion hee had with thée; or elſe I will ſell Cow, Coat, houſe and all, to goe to Law with the Knaue. The old man (her Huſband) perceiuing) that they were all on her ſide, and how that they would not heare him ſpeake in his owne defence: likewiſe thinking if that hee liued with his Wife againe, he muſt be a contented Cuckold, ſaid, Will you heare this? Take your Daughter with you: and I will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently giue her that portion I receiued, and take all this wrong.</p>
               <p>This pleaſed them all; ſo the Prieſt drew a Bill of diuorce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, and the old man deliuered backe her portion, beeing glad that he was rid of his Wife. His wife on the other ſide was glad that ſhe had eſcaped that puniſhment which ſhee deſerued: ſo they all part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſeeming friends.</p>
               <p>I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rry (quoth the Fiſhwife of <hi>Brainford</hi>) this was a wench worth talking of; ſhe deſerueth as much praiſe as thoſe women called <hi>Amazones,</hi> who out of a braue minde cut their huſbands thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ates: and ſo made themſelues, rulers of themſelues.</p>
               <p>But what praiſe (quoth the wife of <hi>Stand on the Greene</hi>) had ſhee deſerued, if ſhe had been diſcouered, or failed in this attempt? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but curſes in my minde, for ſhe had giuen cauſe to all men to ſpeake ill of vs women: it is not the euent, but the honeſty of the intent, that iuſtifies the action. I thinke ſo too, ſaid a Fiſhwife of <hi>Twitnam,</hi> I doe not like this fooliſh hardineſſe: and men are apt to ſpeake ill of vs without cauſe: therefore to make amends, I will tell of a vertuous and chaſte Dame, one whoſe life may bee a mirrour for all women.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="tale">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <head>The deſcription of the Fiſhwife of <hi>Twitnam.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Not old, not young,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Not ſharpe of tongue</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Was this ſame Wife.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She lou'd no ſtrife,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nor much would prate,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But lou'd her mate.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Yet lou'd ſhe lap:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If't were her hap</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To meete with thoſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She knew from foes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:1998:17"/>
                           <hi>She'd ſpend her quart</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>With all her heart.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Well lou'd ſhe Maſſe.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her time ſhe'd paſſe</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In working good:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If neighbours ſtood</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In neede of ought</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She ſold or bought,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>They ſhould it haue,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If they did craue.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This Wife mannerly</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Spake thus ſoberly.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <head>Her Tale.</head>
               <p>SOmetime in Brittaine there raigned a mighty Prince, called <hi>Oſwald,</hi> who for his iuſt gouernment and holy life, had the name of Saint giuen him. This <hi>Oſwald</hi> tooke to his wife a vertuous Maiden, named <hi>Beblam,</hi> daughter to <hi>Kynygils</hi> King of Weſt-Saxons: by whom he had one ſonne, after whoſe birth they willingly agréed (that they might the better ſerue their Sauiour) not to touch one the other after any carnall manner.</p>
               <p>Thus liued this vertuous couple vntill their deaths, onely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtéeming the ſeruice of God, and the auoiding of worldly tentations for their chiefe pleaſure. A Hermet being enuious at the report of his holy life, one day went to him, aſking the King how hee could liue ſo holy, and yet liue with a Wife? To whom the King an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered: Marriage is no hinderance to holy life, for therein doe we but follow the inſtitution of God, which hee ordained for the increaſe of the world: but further to ſatiſfie thée, that it is no hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance to my holy life; take thou this King, and goe to her, bidding her vſe thée as ſhe would vſe my ſelfe.</p>
               <p>The Hermet glad of this (hoping to haue kinde entertainment at his Quéenes hands) went merily to her, deliuering her the King: and told her, that it was her Huſbands will that ſhe ſhould vſe him in all reſpects as ſhee would vſe himſelfe, if hee were there.</p>
               <p>To this the Quéene was willing, and bid him welcome, telling him he ſhould be ſerued in all points as the King her Royall huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was. When the time of ſupper was come, and the Hermet expected ſome delicate cheere, he onely was fed with bread, which was ſerued vp in a ſtately manner, by diuers Gentlemen that did attend him: likewiſe when he called for drink, they gaue him whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome water to coole his hote deſires: no other cates got hee, yet
<pb facs="tcp:1998:17"/>
was it no worſe then the Queene her ſelfe ate of.</p>
               <p>This ſtately ſeruice, and homely fare, ſcarce pleaſed the Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, yet ſtill he hoped for better, but his hopes were vaine, for the cloth was taken vp, and one aſked him if hee pleaſed to goe to bed? To this hee was willing, hoping now to ſleepe out the remembrance of his hard fare: but being come to his Chamber, a ſodaine ioy extinguiſhed the griefe he would haue ſlept out; for he ſaw no worſer woman then the Queene ſhould be his bedfellow. So quickly vndreſſing himſelfe he went in bed to her (not forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting in his thoughts to praiſe her for obeying her Huſbands will) where hauing lyne a while, thinking of ſome ſtrange things, luſt and the euill diſpoſition of his minde beganne to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect his ſoule ſo, that with as kinde imbrace hee beſought the Queene to ſhew ſome mercy towards his hot affection.</p>
               <p>This vertuous Queene ſeeing this Hermet baſely laſciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, rung a Bell: then preſently came in foure women, who took this Hermet and caſt him in a Ciſterne full of water, that ſtood in the Chamber: he being well cooled, they tooke him forth, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing him in the bed as they found him. There hee lay ſhiuering with cold a good ſpace; but at length his bloud being heated, hee fell to thinking with himſelfe: how perchance the Queene ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſelfe thus chaſte, to take ſuſpition from her women, and that ſhe might all the night after play the wanton ſecurely: His burning Luſt, ſeconding this Opinion, made him once more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ducking: ſo turning himſelfe to the Queene, he began with this ſpeech:</p>
               <p>Moſt rare, beauteous, admirable, and vnparalelled woman, I will not onely commend thée for thy beauty, and greatneſſe of Birth and place; but alſo I will adore thee with more then hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane worſhip, for the extraordinarie vnderſtanding which thou haſt aboue others of thy ſexe. With what a graue and ſober carriage doeſt thou hide thy hote affections, which inwardly doe burne thee? Oh it is ſtrange! therewith not onely blinding the eyes of ſtrangers, but alſo thy neereſt attendants: now I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue why thou commandeſt mee to bee hurled in the water Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne, it was thy policy (thou wonder of thy ſexe) to auoid ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in thy ſeruants.</p>
               <p>I knew this well, and therfore did willingly endure the ſame,
<pb facs="tcp:1998:18"/>
that I might the more freely enioy thy beauty now: therewith 'gan he lo clip her in his armes; which ſhee perceiuing, rung the Bell: her women preſently comming in, tooke this Yongſter, ducking him twiſe ſo much as they did before, ſo that they laid him in the bed halfe drowned: and hauing done, preſently voided they the Chamber.</p>
               <p>The Hermet being come to himſelfe, had a better opinion of K. <hi>Oſwald</hi> &amp; his Wife, for he then held them for the holyeſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in England: and his hote bloud being cooled, he lay ſtill that night, not daring to ſtirre, leſt ſhee giuing the alarum, his enemies would come vpon him and put their crueltie in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
               <p>The morning being come, hee kindely tooke his leaue of the Quéene, telling her he had ſufficiently tryed the Kings ſeuere and holy life, and would euer after giue teſtimonie of the ſame: ſo went he to his Cell, being aſhamed of this his fooliſh attempt, and neuer after would looke into other mens liues, but mended his owne.</p>
               <p>She hauing ended her Tale, they all ſaid, This Queene was a vertuous woman, and worthy to bee had in memory, but ſhee was not to be any preſident for them, ſeeing ſhee was a Queene, and they were but Fiſhwiues.</p>
               <p>Truely (quoth a Fiſhwife of <hi>Kingſtone</hi> that fate next to her) if wee would be thus chaſte, alas, our huſbands would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vs to continue to; therefore, for my part, I will neuer goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it: I will tell you a Tale of one that was a great woman (though ſhe was no Queene) and yet kept a friend beſides her huſband.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="tale">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <head>The deſcription of the Fiſhwife of <hi>Kingstone.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This <hi>Kingſtone</hi> wife,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Lou'd little ſtrife.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She was a boſſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That lou'd to toſſe</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The Ale pot round.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Few was there found</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Could with her drinke,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But they would winke,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And fall aſleepe:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Till ſhe would creepe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She'd not giue ore,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But call for more.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Louing the pot,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>All loſt ſhe not:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:1998:18"/>
                           <hi>For ſhe had got</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A noſe full hot,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And red as bloud.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Within it ſtood,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Di'monds ſhining.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Lower declining,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Stood a Rubie.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If I true be,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>There were more</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Then halfe a ſcore,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Which ſhewed like</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The ſparkes you ſtrike,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>From forth a flint:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Such heat was in't.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Men might ſuppoſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>(Seeing her noſe)</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>What broth ſhe lou'd.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>When ſhe had mou'd</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her ſelfe, and ſpit,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She ſpake this writ.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <head>Her Tale.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Certaine great Lady, hauing to her huſband a man old and vnfit to ſatiſfie her youthfull deſires, aſked her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor whether ſhe might not enioy (her deſire being hot, and her huſband vnable) a friend which might ſupply her want, cauſed by her huſbands weakeneſſe? The Fryer (hoping ſhee would make choiſe of him) told her ſhe might, for the ſinne was but little, and did deſerue little or no penance. She thanked him for this kinde abſolution, telling him ſhe onely tooke this carefull courſe, that her huſband might not die without iſſue, hauing his memory buried with him in the duſt.</p>
               <p>The Prieſt (ſtill hoping he was the man ſhe would ſelect) ſaid, her care was good, and no whit offenſiue, if ſhe choſe a friend that would kéepe it from the world. She ſaid, her diligence would chooſe ſuch a one, and ſo they parted: the Prieſt being ſtill in the minde that he ſhould be the man.</p>
               <p>But this Lady meant otherwiſe: for ſhe choſe a Gentleman that ſometime had beene a ſuter vnto her, who louing her deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſhe him, they enioyed each others company without ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of any, onely two of her truſty ſeruants knowing of it.</p>
               <p>The Prieſt perceiuing he was not the man appointed for this buſineſſe, vexed himſelfe in thinking what a foole he was, that he did not make proffer of his ſeruice, when ſhee firſt opened her minde vnto him. Thus thinking of her beauty, and his neglect, hee vowed to performe ſomething which might giue him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; with this reſolue went hee to a pleaſant walke thereby,
<pb facs="tcp:1998:19"/>
where oftentimes the Lady vſed; there hauing obſcured him ſelfe, he might perceiue her with her Louer comming that way. He lying cloſe, and liſtening to heare ſomething that might bee for his aduantage: amongſt other things he heard her aſke, why hee had choſen <hi>Hercules</hi> for his watch-word, ſeeing there were many words, and names, which were more proper to that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? The Prieſt ſtayed not to heare his anſwer, (thinking he had enough in knowing of that word which had the power to bring him to her bed) but cloſely got him home, waiting the comming of night, which he prayed might haſten on, that hee might inioy the pleaſure he ſo wiſhed for.</p>
               <p>To be ſhort, her friend and ſhee parted when they ſaw time, and night being come, ſhe went to bed, where ſhe lay alone: (for her old huſband was at Court:) long had ſhe not lyen there: but the Prieſt (beeing well acquainted with all the turnings in the houſe) came to her Chamber doore and knockt: She aſked who was there? <hi>Hercules,</hi> quoth the Prieſt. With that ſhe roſe, and (thinking it to be her Swéet-heart) let him in. The Prieſt caught her in his armes, kiſſing and vſing other dalliance, ſo long, till hee had fully ſatiſfied his hot deſires: Then quietly tooke hee his leaue without words, which ſhe wondred at.</p>
               <p>Long had he not been gone, when came her Sweet-heart, who ſoftly knocked at the Chamber doore: ſhe hearing it, aſked who was there? <hi>Hercules,</hi> ſaid he. She wondring at his ſudden return, opened the doore, and aſked him why hee came? To enioy thy ſweet company (ſaid hee) and to paſſe away this night in ſuch ſports as ſhall content vs both.</p>
               <p>She wondring to ſee him, and hee not knowing what ſhee meant, (and thinking ſhe miſ doubted his loyaltie) prayed her to tell him the meaning of thoſe words, which ſeemed more ſtrange to him, then rattling Welch, or wilde Iriſh: and he proteſted like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that but euen then he came from his Chamber.</p>
               <p>The Lady now knew that ſhee was deceiued, and that ſome craftie knaue had got at her hands a more then ordinarie kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and 'cauſe he ſhould ſuſpect nothing, ſhe told him that ſhee dreamed ſhe had inioyed his company that night, and that he par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from her after an vnkinde manner.</p>
               <p>Tut, ſaid he, dreames are but falſe ſhaddowes: now haſt thou
<pb facs="tcp:1998:19"/>
the ſubſtance thoſe ſhaddowes did preſent. With ſuch louing words paſſed they the night: and morning being come, her friend kindely tooke his leaue, ſecretly going to his Chamber.</p>
               <p>She being vexed in her minde that ſhe was deceiued, and not knowing by whom, paſſed away that day, hoping ere long to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap her cunning Louer.</p>
               <p>Night being come, after her vſual maner ſhe went to bed, where ſhe had not long beene, but the Prieſt (his appetite being rather ſharpened, then any way ſlacked) came to the doore, ſoftly knoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. She hoping it was he ſhe looked for, went to the doore, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding who was there? <hi>Hercules,</hi> ſaid the Prieſt: ſhe knowing it to be him (by his voice) that had deceiued her, prayed <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> to come in and act a new labour: and vnder colour of vſing him kindely, ſhe felt by the ſhort haire on his head, that it was the Prieſt.</p>
               <p>Being glad ſhe had found her too officious friend, ſhe intreated him to repoſe himſelfe on the bed, till ſhee cleered the houſe of ſome ſeruants that ſhe heard vp in the next roome: to which the Prieſt was very willing, being loth to bee deſcryed at his going forth by any of the houſhold ſeruants.</p>
               <p>But ſhee had another meaning: for ſhee called by her two ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, ſeruants which ſhe truſted with her chiefe ſecrets, bidding them go into her Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, where they ſhould find the Prieſt, whom they ſhould binde, and with a ſharpe knife (which ſhee gaue to them) cut out one of his genitours. They obeying her command, ruſhed into the Chamber, where they found the Prieſt (fearing the noiſe be heard) crept vnder the bed, whom they drew out by the heeles, and bound his hands, and feete. The Prieſt ſéeing them handle him thus roughly, intreated them to forbeare, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he was a Church-man, and it was ſacriledge to offer him violence. He ſéeing this preuailed him nothing, ſet out his throat: but they ſoone ſtopped the ſame, and with a ſharpe knife, and a quick hand, made him lighter by a ſtone.</p>
               <p>Then called they their Lady, who ſeemed to pitie Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> and bid them binde vp his wound, putting thereto ſalue which ſhe gaue them. They hauing done this, ſhee hung a paper about his neck, bidding them vnbinde him, and turne him foorth the doores: which they performed, and ſhutting the doore after him,
<pb facs="tcp:1998:20"/>
they went to bed laughing. The poore Prieſt hyed him home, getting to bed, where he tooke little reſt for the paine hee felt; but he paſſed away the night in curſing the Lady, on whom hee could not tell how to be reuenged. The morning being come, hée eſpyed the writing which hung about his neck; hee opening the ſame, found therein this written:
<q>
                     <l>Prieſt, if that thou chance to tell,</l>
                     <l>What pleaſure through thy wit befell:</l>
                     <l>Likewiſe report not without care,</l>
                     <l>What thou haſt loſt, and what they are:</l>
                     <l>But neuer grieue there's none that can,</l>
                     <l>But muſt confeſſe th'art halfe a man.</l>
                     <l>But leaue thy riding, leſt that ſtone</l>
                     <l>Be carued too, then haſt thou none.</l>
                     <l>So Sir, farewell: th'aſt made amends,</l>
                     <l>For thy deceit: and we are friends.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>At this the Fryer bit his lip, wiſhing he had as much power ouer her life, as he had ouer that paper: but not knowing how to mend himſelfe, but by looking to his wound, hee reſted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe content, and ventured to ſteale no more fleſh: and the Lady inioyed her friend quietly, being neuer after troubled with the Fryer.</p>
               <p>Now tell me (quoth this Fiſhwife) if this Lady bee not as much praiſe-worthy for her wit, as the other was for her hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie? Moſt of them confirmed her argument to be ſound, &amp; the reſt confirmed it by their ſilence. Then the laſt Fiſhwife which was of <hi>Hampton,</hi> ſaid, but for a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the abundance of her wit, to abuſe any man, or her ſelfe, in ſuch diſhoneſt courſes, I thinke it not good: 'cauſe oftentimes the harme which ſhee intendeth, and the ſhame which ſhee deſerueth, lighteth on her ſelfe: which I will make good by this example.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="tale">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <head>The deſcription of the Fiſhwife of <hi>Hampton.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This ſame creature</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Had a feature,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Would haue mou'd</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A man to lou'd.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:1998:20"/>
                           <hi>A body ſound.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A face full round.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A forehead hye.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A full blacke eye.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A ſoft bright haire.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A skin full faire.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A colour ruddy:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And not muddy.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A chin dimpled.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Noſe not pimpled.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She had a lip,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Would make one skip,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To haue a bit:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>So ſweet was it.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Shee'd not lowre.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And looke ſowre.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nor in feaſting,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Be proteſting</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She was no ſuch:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But ſhee'd bide tuch.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Beauties rich ſtore.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And eke much more</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Of honeſt goodneſſe:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And hated lewdneſſe.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <head>Her Tale.</head>
               <p>IN <hi>Deuonſhire</hi> (ſometime) there dwelt a maiden, to whom na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (hauing beene ſomething liberall) gaue ſuch beauty, that ſhe in all mens iudgements was held the comelieſt and faireſt creature in all thoſe parts: ſhe being a right woman, tooke notice of her good parts, &amp; withall grew ſo proud, that ſhe rewarded all thoſe which honeſtly ſought to enioy her loue, either with ſcoffes or vnkinde denials.</p>
               <p>A yong Gentleman of that countrey, long time loued this ſame vnkind and vnmatched creature, but neuer could he receiue better comfort at her hands, then vnkinde anſweres, or ſcornefull lookes. One day (not willing to liue longer betweene hope and feare) hee reſolued to haue of her either a flat deniall, or firme grant; and with this reſolution went to her, to whom he ſpake after this manner:</p>
               <p>Faire <hi>Milliſant,</hi> long time (amongſt other of your ſuters) haue I dearely loued you, yet neuer did I receiue the leaſt token of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance at your hands: diſdaine you my Birth? I am a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, though not deſcended of the higheſt houſes, yet not of the meaneſt. Miſlike you my wealth? I haue enough to maintaine a priuate Gentleman. Miſlike you my parts of body? They are as nature gaue them, I could wiſh they were more pleaſing to your minde. Doe you miſ-doubt my loue to you? Set mee ſome taſke in mans poſſibility to performe, and it ſhall confirme the ſame.
<pb facs="tcp:1998:21"/>
Tell me for what it is you cannot loue me, and I will reforme the ſame, and by faſhioning my ſelfe to your liking, giue you teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of my loue.</p>
               <p>No whit was ſhe moued with his pure loue, but after her v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall manner determined to abuſe the ſame; and to that purpoſe ſhe anſwered him thus:</p>
               <p>Sir, ſuch little libertie hath our ſexe, and men ſuch corrupt iudgements, that our mirth is counted immodeſty, our ciuilleſt lookes laſciuious, our words looſe, our attires wanton, and all our doings apiſh: to ſhunne theſe ſlanders, it behooueth vs to bée carefull ouer our ſelues, and not through our kindneſſes to giue inconſtant and diſſembling men occaſion to ſpeake ill. I taxe not you with this common fault; yet haue I bad no proofe that your loue is any other then diſſembling; therefore till I haue made proofe of the ſame, by your obedience in executing my will, looke not for any kinde fauour at my hands.</p>
               <p>Theſe words gaue him ſome hope: and he being willing to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe his loue to her, deſired her to acquaint him with that taſke whoſe performance would giue him that great happineſſe of her loue: and he vowed to doe it, excepting no danger.</p>
               <p>She ſéeing him thus blinde with her loue, that for her ſake hee would vndergoe any danger, with a cruell and vnmerciful heart vttered theſe words: Sir, I ſhall try you whether your loue is of that pureneſſe you praiſe it for; I charge you, as euer you did reſpect me, or hope to inioy me, for this two yéeres comming to keepe a voluntary ſilence, not ſpeaking to any creature liuing, or to ſing, or vſe any kinde of ſound, whereby your meaning may be vnderſtood: this is my pleaſure, which if you performe not, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſee me: if you will do it, let your ſilence and ſudden departure be ſigne of conſent.</p>
               <p>The Gentleman hearing this vnkind taſke, was almoſt ſtruck dead with griefe, yet ſaid he nothing, but obſeruing her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand, preſently departed with ſilence.</p>
               <p>Being thus ſilenced by that vnmercifull Maid, hee left his friends, and went into <hi>Cornwal,</hi> where he was entertained by the Duke (hee being an excellent Muſician) to teach his children to dance and play on ſundry Inſtruments wherein he had ſkill: In his ſeruice he bore himſelfe ſo worthily, and vſed ſuch diligence
<pb facs="tcp:1998:21"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the childe on that the Duke delighted in his com-paring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> other Gentlemen and ſought all the meanes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> his ſpeech? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſeeing all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> coſt was in vaine, and that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> did him no good, he cauſed it to be publisſhed that whoſoever could reſtore his ſpeech, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pounds ſhould be their reward: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut they not performing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould give the Duke ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or elſe haue impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment till they paid it.  This large, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efull pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe, was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o think that ſhe could with one word doe that which ſo great a Duke could not vndoe, with all his exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> and care She knowing it was in her power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore his ſpeech and being couetous of the great reward, ſhe went into <hi>Cornwall,</hi> proffering her ſelfe before the Duke to performe the cure, or undergoe the puniſhment.</p>
               <p>The Duke being glad that hee had one that would undertake the cure, bid her to take her time for the performance of it; She ſet down three weeks, and that ſhe not performing it in that time, was lyable to his ſharpeſt puniſhments: ſo with a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> courage did ſhe begin her cure.</p>
               <p>The Gentleman ſeeing his hard-hearted Loue come to be his Phyſician, would neither by ſigne, or any word make knowne, that he had any remembrance what ſhe was but ſeemed to her as to a ſtrong <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> though ſhe gaue him many kinde words, ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ing her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> folly in that ſhe knew him not to be of that worth and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation, which ſhe now ſaw he was of.  All this would get ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a word from him; which ſhee ſheeing, intreated to breake that raſh and fooliſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow ſhe had cauſed him to make, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe would giue him ſufficient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of her loue; thus continued ſhe the ſpa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of twelue dayes, but could neuer get any cheerefull looke at his hand: ſhe now fearing he would be reuenged on her, and by his wilfull ſilence ſuffer her either to pay the money, or elſe to lye in priſon with a kinde and louing countenance ſaid theſe words to him:</p>
               <p>Sir if euer you loued me (as you vowed you did) let not my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> be any longer cauſe of your neglecting mee, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> are ſufficient teſtimony of the griefe I haue for  it, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> offer up my loue to you as ſatiſfation for my former
<pb facs="tcp:1998:22"/>
fault: Oh then be mercifull, and louing me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſence, and through my louing duty, let me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> good opinion of me: with theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oying to cauſe him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>All this predaa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed her nothing, for he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her one word: yet with a ſeeming vnwillingneſſe did hee accept her im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces, whe he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> enioyed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>But to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> come, and ſhe could not for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and the Duke ſeeing her folly (he vndertaking his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and not performing it) cauſed her to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> (not being able to pay the money <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe had cured him) till ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.  That time being come, he went to the Duke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him to pardon his long wilfull ſilence, pauſed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, withall felling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and how he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>The Duke was exceeding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him ſpeake, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> praiſed his wit for vſing ſo vngentle a perſon ſo vntowardly: yet blamed him withall, for keeping ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and vnreaſonable a vow ſo ſtraightly: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> both hauing had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> enough for their folly, hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> them both, continuing his loue to the Gentleman, and rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ng her, who by that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> has got a great belly with her awiſe phyſicke, but he that owed the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rait, would not acknowledge it: ſo that ſhee was to looke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> new cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomer, or elſe endure the open ſhame belonging to a S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: which of them ſhe did, I know not, eyther of them was bad e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: and had that Gentlewoman had no better fortune in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing the Fryer, then this by exerciſing her with on this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, ſhee had deſerued no more then this fooliſh woman doth.</p>
               <p>It is ture (ſaid the <hi>Brainford</hi> Fiſhwife:) and ſince it conernes vs not, let vs leaue this <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>contra,</hi> let euery tub ſtand on it owne bottome: and ſo our mirth and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ourney ends about one time: for yonder is <hi>Kingſtone,</hi> whoſe large and conſcion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able pots are praiſed throughout England; whoſe Ale is of great ſtrength and force, as our Weſterne Watermens ſicke
<pb facs="tcp:1998:22"/>
braines can witneſſe. Then ſince it is ſo neere, let vs not bee factious, and contend for trifles; but let vs ſeeke to enioy that which we came for, mirth; that beſt preſeruer of our liues: ſo land vs with all ſpeed, honeſt Waterman.</p>
               <p>They hearing her ſpeake but reaſon, agréed to be ruled by her, and therefore gaue her the name of Captaine. With all haſte (and eaſe) as I could poſſible, landed I my merry Fare of Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiues, who went ſtraight to the ſigne of the Beare, where they found ſuch good liquor, that they ſtayed by it all night: where I left them, and ſo ended my iourney, <hi>Weſtward for Smelts.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
